Finding Aid for the Cole Family Papers LSC.0217
UCLA Library Special Collections
White, Stephen M.
Williams, George H.
Wilmington, California. Box 3/folder 1871.
Wilson, T. Woodrow.
Wood, Leonard. Box 14/folder 1916.
Women's Suffrage Association.
Wordon, Slater D.
World War I.
Yates, Richard.
Yosemite Valley, California.
Addenda to the Subject Index
A List of subjects and persons in selected references in the papers contained in added boxes 44-50, 56-60, and 63.
Alabama Claims.
Alaska Purchase, 1867. Box 50/folder 3.
Bayard, Thomas F.
California Citrus Industry:
California Lands and Real Property:
California Reclamation of Land:
Cole, Cornelius.
Cole Family: Business papers: Boxes 56-59.
Cole Family Law Partnerships (Cole and Cole, Los Angeles; Cole and Brown, Los Angeles): Boxes 44-46.
Cole, Seward.
Cole, Willoughby.
Currency Question. Box 50/folder 3.
Flint, Frank P.
Grant, Jesse.
Grant, Ulysses S. Jr.
Los Angeles, Hollywood High School.
Huntington, Collis P. Box 47/folder 1.
Los Angeles.
Los Angeles Harbor Controversy.
Mexico. Box 50/folder 2.
Needham, James C. Letter: Box 49/folder 3.
Perkins, George C.
Seward, Frederick W.: Letter, Box 49/folder 3.
Spalding, Albert G.
Stephens, William D. Letter: Box 49/folder 3.
Sutter, John A. Box 56/folder 2.
White, S.M. 4 letters: Box 49/folder 1.
Worden, Salter D. 10 letters: Box 49/folder 3.
World War I. Box 65.
Pioneers -- California -- Archives.; Family papers.; Letters (Correspondence).; Legislators -- Archives.; Lawyers -- California -- Archives.; Diaries.; Cole family--Archives.; Cole, Cornelius, 1822-1924--Archives.; Cole, Olive C., 1832 or 1833-1918--Archives.; Cole, Cornelius; Cole, Olive C.
- Correspondence of Cornelius Cole, 1851-1924; (Approximately 4000 pieces)
  - Cornelius Cole to Various Persons, 1856-1923
    - 1856-1866, 40 pieces. (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Drafts and copies of letters concerning early California politics, the Democratic party, the administration of James Buchanan, the Kansas controversy, David C. Broderick, William H. Seward, the Republican National Committee, candidates for the presidency in 1860, politics and conditions in Washington, D.C., the burning of Richmond, currency issues, the Russian Fur Company.
    - 1867-1872, 35 pieces. (Box 1)
      Drafts and copies of letters concerning California politics, John Conness, the impeachment of Andrew Johnson, members of the U.S. Senate, Baron de Stoeckl and Russian-American affairs, the Treaty of Washington, the arrest and trial of George W. Cole.
    - 1872-1879, 8 pieces. (Box 1)
      Drafts and copies of letters concerning the California and Texas Railroad, the Centennial Exposition in Philadelphia, Cole's finances.
    - 1880-1912, 18 pieces. (Box 1)
      Drafts and copies of letters concerning James A. Garfield and possible appointments to his Cabinet, real estate in California, mining claims in Oregon Canyon, California, the career of the Cole brothers and their companions in the gold fields, 1849-1851, Adolph Spreckels and the tariff on sugar, Wesleyan University, the election and Republican convention of 1912, facts in the case of the impeachment of Andrew Johnson.
    - 1913-1919, 64 pieces. (Box 1)
      Drafts and copies of letters concerning Cole's Memoirs, the policies of Woodrow Wilson and the world situation, German warfare, the Republican Convention in Chicago in 1916, Hiram Johnson, Elihu Root, Theodore Roosevelt, Will H. Hays, the strength of Republicans in California, Cole's copy of Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation.
    - 1920-1923, 90 pieces. (Box 1)
      Drafts and copies of letters concerning Hiram Johnson, Wesleyan University, Henry E. Huntington, Calvin Coolidge, William G. McAdoo, Lincoln's Gettysburg Address and Emancipation Proclamation. Letter to R. Von Klein [????].
    - 1917-1923, 28 pieces. (Box 1)
      Drafts and copies of letters to Warren G. Harding, as Senator from Ohio and President of the United States, concerning Woodrow Wilson's foreign Policy, the world situation, Harding's candidacy at the Republican Convention in 1920, and disarmament.
  - Cornelius Cole to Various Persons, 1883-1912
    - Drafts and copies of letters, 1883-1908; 45 pieces. (Box 47, Folder 1)
      Including letters to Samuel Stevens concerning the Alabama claims cases, reclamation of lands in California, Cole real estate, Los Angeles Harbor controversy, letter to Collis P. Huntington, Hollywood High School.
    - Drafts and copies of letters, 1909-1912; 50 pieces. (Box 47, Folder 2)
      Including letters to George C. Perkins on the subject of the tariff on lemons, to A.G. Spalding on the subject of his senatorial campaign, letters to members of the Los Angeles city council on the subject of street names.
  - Various Persons to Cornelius Cole, 1851-1870
    - 1851-1859, 48 pieces. (Box 2)
      Letters and papers concerning the John C. Fremont campaign in California in 1856, the Republican National Committee, preparations for the Convention of 1860, envelope containing letters of Edward Stanley concerning Republican strength in the state, speeches, factions and personalities in politics, 1857; letters of F.P. Tracy concerning cases in San Francisco and Fremont Clubs in the mines; 2 letters from A.A. Sargent from Nevada City, California during the campaign of 1854, 4 letters from James Pratt concerning the Negro extradition case in 1852; 9 letters from E.D. Morgan concerning the Philadelphia Republican Convention of 1856 and the Fremont campaign.
    - 1860-1862, 12 pieces. (Box 2)
      Letters and papers concerning the Republican National Committee, their Convention of 1860, appointments and problems of the new Lincoln administration, San Francisco lands, 3 letters from F.P. Tracy concerning appointments, Seward's candidacy, delegates to the Convention, Fremont's political strength.
    - 1863-1865, 80 pieces. (Box 2)
      Letters and papers concerning lands and mining properties in California, state politics and appointments, Idaho Territory, solicitation for the influence of Lincoln and his Cabinet, the Pacific railroad, Salmon P. Chase, Benjamin F. Butler, Nathaniel P. Banks, Leland Stanford, letters from Frederick W. Seward, James W. Simonton on Californians in the Lincoln Cabinet, from William H. Seward on appointments in 1865, F.F. Low on office-holders in California, reference to General George B. McClellan, letter from James W. Simonton in 1865 mentioning Frederick Billings, John Conness; letter from A.A. Sargent, 1863; 6 letters from Sargent, 1864 and 3 in 1865 concerning California politics, campaigns, F.F. Low, state lands; letters from Stephen J. Field, Elihu B. Washburne; letter from Gideon Welles, Generals R.C. Drum and James Carleton; letter from William P. Fessenden; Benjamin F. Butler, Frederick Billings concerning the Overland Mail Company and Ben Holladay; five letters from Asa Biggs concerning George W. Cole's promotion, B.F. Butler and Ambrose Burnside; 3 letters from George Bradbury concerning the China Mail bill; letter from Peter H. Burnett concerning Lincoln's proclamation of amnesty; invitation from Salmon P. Chase; 5 letters from E.B. Crocker concerning the construction, finance, legislation and progress of the Central Pacific Railroad, telegraph projects, the Pacific Mail Company, Wells, Fargo Company; 2 letters from H.H. Haight concerning appointments; letter from Edward Stanley Concerning California ranchos; 8 letters from Allan T. Lane concerning routes, finance, legislation of the Pacific Mail Steamship Company, with mention of Cornelius Vanderbilt; letter from E.D. Morgan concerning the Republican National Committee.
    - 1866-1870, 75 pieces. (Box 2)
      Letters and papers concerning the Civil Rights bill, opinions of Andrew Johnson, impeachment of Johnson, Grant and the election of 1868, diplomatic problems and the possibility of war with England, the Cole public lands bill, the California wine industry, U.S. consul in Munich, Bavaria, California railroads, the ocean telegraph project, Alaska and Pacific Mail Steamship Company, naval contracts and politics in California, American commerce in China, Santo Domingo, the acquittal of George W. Cole. 2 letters of Charles Maltby mentioning Orville H. Browning and discussing Maltby's friendship with Lincoln, 1866; 3 letters from F.F. Low on state politics and business and the possible appointment of a Californian or Oregonian as Secretary of the Interior, 1868; 2 letters from A.A. Sargent; 4 letters from Abel Stearns concerning the litigation over Rancho Temescal, mention of Stephen J. Field, 1866-1867; 2 letters from Leland Stanford mentioning Collis P. Huntington; letter from Edward Stanley concerning the election of Ulysses S. Grant; Documents and papers relating to Rancho Temescal; 5 letters from Schuyler Colfax mentioning Hugh McCulloch, Andrew Johnson and John Defrees; letter from C.A. Seward, Lyman Trumbull, General Edward Ord, George Bancroft; 9 letters in envelope from Thompson Campbell discussing California politics, and mentioning Stephen J. Field, Andrew Johnson's administration and impeachment, Richard Yates of Illinois, Grant, E.B. Washburne, Senator Eugene Casserly of California; letter from Leland Stanford concerning Cole's election and Negro suffrage, and the status of the Southern states; 3 letters from Collis P. Huntington concerning California appointments.
  - Various Persons to Cornelius Cole, 1871-1879
    - 1871, 125 pieces. (Box 3)
      Letters and papers concerning Senator Charles Summer, the London Mint, English capital to reclaim California lands, expenses and appointments in the Republican party, San Diego politics, University of California, campaign of A.A. Sargent, U.S. Currency, Indian affairs in Arizona, New York and the Mexican Steamship Company, legal status of war taxation, membership of Congressional Committees, consul in Rome. Letters from John A. Logan; letter from George Robeson, Secretary of the Navy; 2 letters from F.F. Low on the Chinese Indemnity Fund, and foreign students and residence; letter from H.H. Bancroft; 4 letters from Robert J. Stevens mentioning William Belknap, Columbus Delano, Newton Booth--A. A. Sargent Senatorial contest, Orville E. Babcock, Grant, James G. Blaine, John Bidwell, Collis P. Huntington, Edward Baker as possible Secretary of the Interior, 1861, California editors, support of Cole for re-election, situation in Washington, D.C.; 2 letters from A. Willard concerning extradition case in Mexico, Baja California colonization, San Domingo; 6 letters from J.B.M. Stewart concerning the Central Polynesian Land and Commercial Company, the project, difficulties, Samoa and Pago Pago, opposition from London, Ambrose Burnside; 3 letters from W.A. Selkirk concerning election of A.A. Sargent; letter from Amos T. Akerman, U.S. Attorney General; 3 letters from Phineas Banning concerning the harbor breakwater at Wilmington, Los Angeles, and riots in Los Angeles; 5 letters from John Bidwell concerning politics and corruption, A.A. Sargent, Oliver P. Morton a guest of Cole; 2 letters from Hannibal Hamlin, mention of G.M. Dodge; letter from E.C. Ingersoll concerning Senate contest in CALIFORNIA; letter from H.H. Haight mentioning Oliver P. Morton and Francis P. Blair; 2 letters from Collis P. Huntington concerning the Central Pacific Railroad.
    - 1872, 35 pieces. (Box 3)
      Letters and papers concerning the Texas-Pacific railroad, the Samoan Islands, United States financial policy, the issue of reform in politics, the Caribbean trade, real estate in California. Letters from James W. Simonton mentioning Goat Island, San Francisco, bill then pending, influence of the Central Pacific railroad upon that matter, the low point of popularity of the Grant administration, San Domingo; letter from John Sherman, Secretary of the Treasury George Boutwell; Attorney General George H. Williams concerning Pacific Islands, mentioning Secretary of State Hamilton Fish; 2 letters from John Bidwell; letter from Newton Booth concerning removal of the Modoc Indians in California; letter from Hamilton Fish to Attorney General Williams concerning Pacific Islands.
    - 1873-1875, 60 pieces. (Box 3)
      Letters and papers concerning the Pacific Mail Steamship Company, Central Polynesian Land and Commerce Company, the Texas-Pacific railroad, the University of California, mining claims in California, Zachariah Chandler as Secretary of the Interior, Grant's Cabinet, corruption in the Land office and Indian Bureau, appointments in the Treasury Department. Letters from James W. Simonton, 1873; William R. Grace, steamship line financier, Daniel C. Gilman of the University of California; Benjamin H. Bristow, E.B. Washburne; card from William T. Sherman; 5 letters from Gabriel K. Stevenot concerning guano deposits in Peru, papers relative to that subject; 5 letters from John A. Bingham concerning Pacific Mail Steamship Company route; letter from Newton Booth concerning Modoc Indians; letter from Senator Eugene Casserly mentioning Oliver P. Morton; letter from S.S. Cox and Mrs. Cox; letter from Frederick W. Seward.
    - 1876-1879, 35 pieces. (Box 3)
      Letters and papers concerning Society of California Pioneers, California stocks and real estate, bill to remonetize silver, New Constitution Party in California, Dennis Kearny, third term controversy, mining boom in Arizona. Letters from Senator John Jones of Nevada, E.B. Washburne; Admiral E.G. Parrott.
  - Various Persons to Cornelius Cole, 1880-1921
    - 1880-1898, 80 pieces. (Box 4)
      Letters and papers concerning California silk culture, the national elections of 1884 with the consequences to be expected from the Democratic victory and the reason for the Republican defeat, Senators Roscoe Conkling and James G. Blaine, Republican League of California, Wesleyan University, obsequies of James A. Garfield in San Francisco, Los Angeles fruit growers, conditions in Arizona, conditions in northern Mexico, Court of Commissioners for the Alabama Claims, local campaign literature for 1893, Historical Society of Southern California, Attorney General Richard Olney, Alaska fisheries, bank panics in 1894, pioneer conditions in Oregon Valley, California, political strength of William J. Bryan and William McKinley in California counties, Collis P. Huntington, citrus fruits in Congressional committee deliberations. Letters from Samuel Clemens and his wife Olivia, 1898, mentioning Spain and Cuba's acquisition by the U.S., 2 letters from Senator Stephen White; letter from Senator W. B. Allison; letter from Senator John Jones concerning citrus tax; 3 letters from Senator George Perkins concerning U.S. Financial policy and legislation, 1893-1894; letter from Charles Maltby concerning Lincoln article; letter from Thomas F. Bayard concerning English laws pertaining to postal savings; letter from C.W. Fullerton of Chicago; 2 letters from Representative Charles A. Barlow concerning U.S. bonds; letter from James G. Blaine sending letter of introduction for Emma Cole; letter from Cassius M. Clay concerning his role in the Alaska Purchase; letter from Senator George F. Edmunds of Vermont; letter from President-Elect James A. Garfield concerning the effect of the forged Chinese letter on his election in California; letter from Senator William Stewart of California; J.H. Mitchell of Oregon; and Douglas Tilden, sculptor; 6 letters from Collis P. Huntington concerning the Central Pacific Railroad and the Los Angeles Harbor.
    - 1901-1909, 58 pieces. (Box 4)
      Letters and papers concerning Cole's Memoirs, Andrew Johnson, Republican campaign of 1856, George W. Cole, Senator Stewart. Letter from Salter D. Worden, leader of strikers in California strike of 1894; letter from William W. Morrow; letter from General Adna Chaffee; letter from Annie E.K. Bidwell, wife of John Bidwell; letter from William Frost concerning Cassius M. Clay and the Alaska Purchase.
    - 1910-1914, 58 pieces. (Box 4)
      Letters and papers concerning Cole's Memoirs, inquiries about the various copies of Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation, the campaign of William H. Taft in 1912. Letter from H.H. Bancroft; letter from Senator George Perkins, concerning Theodore Roosevelt and the Republican party in California; 4 letters from George F. Edmunds, mentioning Andrew Johnson, W.P. Fessenden, Lyman Trumbull; 2 letters from Rockwell D. Hunt; letter from R.M. Brereton concerning Cole's irrigation and lands legislation.
    - 1915-1918, 50 pieces. (Box 4)
      Letters and papers concerning Theodore Roosevelt and the Progressive party, support of Charles E. Hughes in the Republican Convention of 1916, the United Republicans of Southern California, the Republican National Committee, Wilson's foreign policy, U.S. participation in the World War, the Worden espionage case, death of Olive Cole. 3 letters from Rockwell D. Hunt; letter from Secretary of State Robert Lansing concerning U.S. shipping destroyed by England and Germany; letter from Senator James Watson; letter from Will H. Hays, 1918.
    - 1916-1921, 25 pieces (1 missing). (Box 4)
      Letters from Warren G. Harding concerning the Republican party, Wilson's administration and foreign policy.
    - 1919-1921, 55 pieces. (Box 4)
      Letters and papers concerning the Treaty of Versailles, the League of Nations, Wilson, the Republican National Conventions of 1860 and 1920, Hiram Johnson, history of Lake Tahoe, Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation, Wesleyan University, California Republicans and the election of 1864, Cole's birthdays. Letters from Senators Frank Brandegee, Boise Penrose, Samuel Shortridge; letter from Hiram Johnson on the Senate and the League of Nations; letter from Will H. Hays; 5 letters from Charles F. Lummis; 8 letters from Henry E. Huntington concerning Cole's Memoirs, real estate, and copy of the Emancipation Proclamation.
  - Various Persons to Cornelius Cole, 1877-1892
    - Letters, 1877-1887; 10 pieces. (Box 48, Folder 1)
      Concerning the reclamation of lands in California; Los Angeles county railroads; location of Soldiers' Home near Cole property; Letter T.F. Bayard.
    - Letters and papers, 1888; 70 pieces. (Box 48, Folder 2)
      Concerning the litigation of the Alabama claims under Cole's charge and interest, the finances of private parties therein concerned, relations with other claims lawyers in Washington, D.C. and California, especially Samuel Stevens, James Lowndes, and Shellabarger and Wilson. Letters concerning Los Angeles county railroad.
    - Letters and papers, 1889; 80 pieces. (Box 48, Folder 3)
      Concerning the litigation of the Alabama claims cases, continued, and the private financial and legal transactions therein involved; letters mainly from Samuel Stevens.
    - Letters and papers, 1890-1899; 110 pieces. (Box 48, Folder 4)
      Concerning the litigation of the Alabama claims cases, continued, and the private financial and legal transactions therein involved. Letters concerning Cole real estate, the reclamation of lands in California, road improvements of same.
  - Various Persons to Cornelius Cole, 1893-1923
    - Letters and papers, 1893-1894; 60 pieces. (Box 49, Folder 1)
      Concerning the sale, use and reclamation of lands in California, and of Cole real estate, state legislation concerning same.
    - Letters, 1896-1902; 25 pieces. (Folder 2)
      Concerning the Los Angeles Harbor controversy; leasing of Cole land for oil drilling.
    - Letters, 1904-1912; 80 pieces. (Box 49, Folder 3)
      Concerning administration of Hollywood High School; the case of Salter D. Worden and Cole's efforts to obtain a pardon for him, including 10 Worden letters; letters from California Senators and Congressmen discussing the course of proposed tariff bill on lemons, including 1 James C. Needham letter, 5 letters from George C. Perkins, one letter from William D. Stephens, and 6 letters from Frank P. Flint; Letters concerning the senatorial campaign of A.G. Spalding, including comment on his opponent, John D. Works, 3 Spalding letters.
    - Letter from F.W. Seward V.P. to C. Cole., 1913-1923 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Various Persons to Cornelius Cole, 1922-1924
    - 1922, 140 pieces. (Box 5)
      Letters and papers concerning Cole's 100th birthday, Lincoln and his Gettysburg Address, the days of 1849 in the gold mines and early California, the Alaska Purchase, Society of California Pioneers, Wesleyan University, University of Southern California. Letter from Charles F. Lummis, from John Hays Hammond, from Carl F. Rosecrans; telegram from J.L. Giannini.
    - 1923, 130 pieces. (Box 5)
      Letters and papers concerning Cole's 101st birthday, Sutter's Fort, Lincoln and his Gettysburg Address, Society of California Pioneers, Wesleyan University, University of Southern California, Alaska Purchase, Los Angeles. Letter from C. Bascom Slemp, secretary to President Calvin Coolidge, R. Hunt, letter from William G. McAdoo, telegram from Douglas Fairbanks Jr.
    - 1924, 90 pieces. (Box 5)
      Letters and papers concerning Cole's 102nd birthday, early California, Lincoln, Wesleyan University. Telegram from Frank O. Lowden.
  - Cornelius Cole to Olive Cole, 1861-1867
    - 1861-1862, 72 pieces. (Box 6)
      Letters written from Sacramento and San Francisco concerning politics, court cases, abolition, the removal of George B. McClellan.
    - 1863, 96 pieces. (Box 6)
      Letters written from San Francisco, during voyage via Panama, and from Washington, D.C. concerning the Emancipation Proclamation, the Pacific railroad, depreciation of legal tender, conditions in the capitol in wartime, Californians in Congress.
    - 1864, 75 pieces. (Box 6)
      Letters from Washington, D.C. concerning debates in Congress, the conscription bill, foreign affairs, the Pacific railroad, Jubal Early's raid near the capitol, Schuyler Colfax, James A. Garfield, Reverdy Johnson, a meeting with President Lincoln, a dinner with William H. Seward.
    - 1865, 55 pieces. (Box 6)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning Congressional debates on currency standard, the consideration of the 13th Amendment in the House of Representatives, a levy at the White House, Benjamin Butler, the burning of the Smithsonian Institution, Lincoln and Edwin Stanton at a lecture, the Pacific railroad, the vote in Congress on the 13th Amendment, a military prison camp in the North, receptions and parties at the residences of Seward, Gideon Welles, William Dennison, Stanton, the China Mail bill, movements of the armies, investments in oil, Fernando Wood, Californians in Washington, Collis P. Huntington, the inauguration of Lincoln, correspondence with Alexander Gardner, the photographer.
    - 1866, 58 pieces. (Box 6)
      Letters from Washington, D.C. and elsewhere concerning Seward, Andrew Johnson, members of Johnson's Cabinet, Collis P. Huntington, Negro celebration, Reconstruction problems, the Philadelphia Convention of Johnson supporters, the Pacific railroad, the Russian Fur Company, Baltimore, Maryland, the campaign of 1866.
    - 1867, 30 pieces. (Box 6)
      Letters from Washington, D.C. and elsewhere concerning the arrest of George W. Cole, Ulysses S. Grant as Secretary of War, Baron Edward de Stoeckl and Russian-American affairs, Collis P. Huntington, voyage via Panama.
  - Cornelius Cole to Olive Cole, 1868-1872
    - 1868, 23 pieces. (Box 7)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C., Albany, New York, en route overland to California, Sacramento concerning the trial of George W. Cole, newspaper criticism of George and Cornelius Cole, the Pacific railroad, Roscoe Conkling, Louis Jean Agassiz, Anson Burlingame, description of Chicago, Omaha, Nebraska, Fort Bridger, Wyoming Territory, Salt Lake City, the Mormons, Leland Stanford, local California politics, excursion on the Central Pacific railroad.
    - 1869, 18 pieces. (Box 7)